World War II letters, 1941-1946
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
World War II letters, 1941-1946
M1240
Rube family
1 Linear feet 1mb, 1half mb, and 1 flat
162 letters, most with corresponding envelopes
Includes correspondence from the seven Rube brothers and their family members during World War II. They write of their activities and experiences, both from Europe and the South Pacific and the home front.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: speccollref@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc/university-archives
Administrative Information
Provenance
This collection was purchased from Charles Apfelbaum Books by Stanford University, Special Collections in 2001.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Biographical/Historical note
The Rube brothers--David, Conrad, Scott, William, Henry, John, and Peter--were from Fresno, California and all served in World War II. According to one newspaper clipping found in the collection, the brothers believed they held a national record as the largest group of siblings serving in the same war at the same time. At the war's conclusion, all seven brothers were alive.
Scope and Contents
Includes correspondence from six of the seven Rube brothers and their family members during World War II. They write of their activities and experiences, both from Europe and the South Pacific and the home front. Also included are 8 negatives, 1 set of dog tags, printed ephemera including newsclippings about the brothers, and one uniform jacket. The four Rube sisters, Anne, Katherine, Margie, and Emma, are featured as well as domestic issues the family faced while the brothers were overseas.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged series by author. Within each series the letters are arranged chronologically.
Access Terms
Charles Apfelbaum Books; United States--History; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945 --Personal narratives, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945–-Campaigns--Pacific Area.
Collection Contents
- Series 1: Letters from the family to David Rube
  - [Card]: Infantry replacement training center – Camp Hood, Texas (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter from John Rube (father) to David (July 6, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    • Received a letter from Henry – wrote on June 27 & Henry saw John June 26, 1945. Henry said: John looks nice and showed Scott’s pictures; Scott and Pete went to the Pacific; Read that one division stays in Germany; The 80th division is assigned to Germany; The week before, found out that Willie is in the Philippines • In the letter, talked about Camp Hood, Texas & its appearance – in good shape • Mentioned a bill they received for $18.81 • Thought they had lost their dog, Fitze, but after 3 days the dog came back
  - Letter from Dad, Mother, and Sister (August 15, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    • Dave sent a birthday card + $5 to family member [money is not in letter] • Brothers/Boys from the Pacific will come home because the fighting had stopped--Will take months or a year them to come home--The ones that will come home sooner are the ones with high points (Henry- 78pts, John- 53pts) • Mentions difficulties at home & how they long for him to come home. Difficulties include peaches ripe, struggling to eat • Mentions they have not received letters from Scott since July 26, 1945 • Willie [William] got malaria • They wrote a letter to William, John, and Connie [Conrad] • Willie wrote them letters in May and June • Willie wrote to Anne
  - Letter from Dad, Mother, and Sister (September 18, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    • They received a letter from Henry that day mentioning that all they were doing was guard duty • They received a letter from John who mentioned that he is in Luzon, Philippines • Willie is somewhere near Henry & Willie feels better after malaria • Connie is on his way to the U.S. but hasn’t landed yet • Received a letter from Peter on May 16, 1945 • Scott is in Staunton,Virginia • Dad wants to send him grapes • In letter they talk about the pay
  - Letter from Dad, Mother, and Sister to David (Oct. 3, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    • They had barely received letter he wrote them from September 18, 1945 • Mentioned that they are aware he will go overseas soon • Talks about the hot weather • Conrad is there on the ranch – has his discharge now
  - Letter from John Rube – [possibly Connie wrote for him] (Oct. 4, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    • He wants David to get a furlough [vacation/time-off] for 15 – 20 days • He hasn’t seen him since 1941 • John joined the federal armed forces in 1941
  - Letter to Dave from Anne (September 21, 1945) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    • Sent him a paper to sign in order to open a bank account for him since she has $100 saved for him • Willie isn’t sending any money to save—doubts that he’s saving any money • Willie is headed to Japan • Connie’s mail is coming back—she doesn’t know if he’s coming home • John is headed for Japan • Scott landed in Virginia almost 2 weeks ago
  - Letter to Dave from Katherine [Kay, sister] (September 21, 1945) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    • Thanks him for the birthday card & money • She wishes that he can get a furlough because she really wants to see him • Asks him to send a picture • Says that she wants her man home [her man is not Dave]
  - Letter to Dave from Anne (October 12, 1945) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    • Is mad that Dave hasn’t wrote her in several weeks • Connie was discharged & is staying at Anne’s place • Pete sent a telegram saying he coming home very soon • Katherine told her that John landed in Japan • Willie was in Japan • Believes that Hank should be coming home in Dec • Saw Mary & Dick • Margie is a baby & can say a couple of words
- Series 2: Letters from Conrad Rube
  - Letter from Conrad to Anne Rube (July 8, 1941) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    • Background: He was at San Luis Obispo, CA Service Company, 185th Infantry (R) • He writes her that she is wrong about him being on kitchen patrol (K.P). There is no time for him to be in the kitchen or write a letter when he wants to • He works at night—often until midnight & sometimes later than that • Went to the camp theater a few times—Sundays if he does • Talked about the funny experiences he has had – ex: 4th of July • He sold the car to Manuel—to pick Anne up. Conrad thinks Manuel is the perfect guy for her • He is not able to write more than one letter every 6 weeks or so, never more • Talks about the weather • Talks about the different draftees – coming from Chicago, NY • In the regiment he was in, John Seib & Carl Wenig were there • Asks about the crops at home • Asks if dad needs money • Talked about Emma – [sister] and that she makes corrections about his punctuation.
  - Postcard from Conrad to John G. Rube—Father (Dec. 10, 1941) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    • Conrad is no longer at Camp San Luis Obispo but is in Southern California • Talks about how people don’t realize how the army has the right of way at all times • Cannot give information on locality
  - Letter from Conrad to Dave (June 9, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 2)
    • Questions his brother on why he has to know how many battle scars each brother is entitled to • Tells him to write slower because there are many mistakes in his letter • Talks about how he needs relaxation sometimes in order from him going insane—reason for not writing/having time to write letters
- Series 3: Letter from G. Scott Rube
  - Letter to Dave from Scott (May 9th [no year noted], Location—Austria) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    • The war is over • Feelings: he felt relieved, he no longer had to hear that army/war talk • He’s in Austria waiting to find out where they will go to next • He wants to go to the States • Near death experience –The Last Big Fight • The ammunition shot out of carbine (rifle) by two people waiting for him when he came around the corner of a building. Both shot at him; the first one missing & the second hitting his carbine (rifle) – He was lucky • When he was in Nuremburg, Germany he had the chance to observe some of the results of their air forces bombing • He went on five or so bombing missions when he was with the air force
  - Letter to Dave from Scott (July 19, 1945; location—Paris, France) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    • Scott has received a stack of mail—first mail he has received since November • Scott is no longer with the 80th Division • After VE day they were given physicals & Scott did not pass because of a fever, sinus, attack of asthma, & an old wound • He went through several hospitals & after was sent to a “Special Service Bn” outside of Paris—only 1 week before he got scarlet fever & was at the hospital for 25 more days • They wanted to send him back on duty but he told them he was taken out of his division because he had something wrong • He didn’t want to get reassigned—he liked the 80th division because they’ll go back to the US soon • He tried talking to his connections to get Dave out of the army or at least from going overseas –The other 6 brothers (including Scott) were already overseas at this point
  - Letter to Everyone from Scott (December 1, 1944, location—England) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    • He was in England, probably for 3 more weeks. • Went to London & visited several historical spots • Explained what he learned
- Series 4: Letters from William Rube
  - Letter to Dave from Bill (April 13, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    • Dave was possibly the last to join the army • Bill mentions how he knows it’s a tough place but knows that he can do it • Says that the Army can teach him two things: make him a man and make him appreciate life, learn about life & get along with different people • It was hard for Bill to get used to it, but realized that at the end they are all human • Bill doesn’t want to tell Dave what to do, but is just giving him advice
  - Letter to Dave from Bill (May 20, 1945, Location—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    • Talks about being in the Philippines • Talks about the food there, how he trades for cigarettes • Bill got a letter from John - He knows that he is close to Connie maybe even on the same island
  - Letter to Dave from Bill (Sept 4 1945, Location—Philippines) (Box 1, Folder 4)
    • Bill didn’t write him sooner because he didn’t know his location • Mentions that Dave has finished his training and now knows the life of being a soldier • Bill gives Dave advice: that every night he should hurry & dig in so he won’t get hurt. Bill digs in every night and moves & the move never seems to end • Talked about fun moments at the camp, getting drunk, etc. • Bill tells him to make sure to put full serial number on letters, regulations
- Series 5: Letters from David Rube
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (May 26, 1944) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • He talks about how they will not come home any time soon • If Peter is in the "15 Army" he won’t come home either –asks if she knows what Army Pete is in • Wrote letters 2-3 weeks
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (March 2, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Doesn’t know where he is at but he’s up NORTH • Tells her to get rid of all the clothes he left
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (March 26, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • He’s in the hospital—he broke his wrist watch when he first got there • He had a pretty bad cold & had a temp of 103 degrees
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (April 2, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Asked her to send Willie’s Basie Field Manual Book • Two men that they knew were killed and 10 were injured • 3 weeks before that a captain was killed • They haven’t had any snow at all
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (April 15, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Anne sent him a handkerchief and candy & he told her he’ll pay her back for which he gets paid at the end of the month • Talked about how the weeks will be tough • He went to church in the morning & evening on Sunday – goes whenever he has time
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (April 22, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Assumes that Peter must be in battle again • Anne sends Dave candy & cookies • Dave was at the hospital due to a cold • President died • He gets good food where he’s stationed • He was in rifle range that passed week & scored 161 pts. out of 200 • Made a total of 192 pts. if 200 – meaning those were good shots • Tells her that he will send about $50 to save for when he goes home
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (April 30 [no year noted]) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Received a package from Anne & liked it • Hot weather • Marched 20 miles • Received letter from Pete & Willie • Sent $2 for Easter to Margie [sister ] [money is not in envelope]
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (May 6, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Only has 8 weeks of training left • When he finishes, he doesn’t know what will happen or where he will go • Received letters from Willie, Henry, and Pete • Told Ann to send him a picture of his brothers • Will send another $50 money order • Received a package she sent • He tells her to write the brothers & to tell him if anyone is located near him
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (May 10, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Sent her $50 to put in a safe place [physical money not in envelope, but light blue receipt for remitter #12357 is]
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (May 20, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Was glad she received the money • He received a letter from Henry • Scott doesn’t really write because Dave already sent him 4 letters • They are not allowed to get pictures & he told her to use the camera when she wants • He told her to take pictures & send them to the boys
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (June 25, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Asked to get Fred Priez address • Went to church • Bought a radio but needs to get it fixed Sent her $5 to put in a safe place [physical money not in envelope, but light blue receipt for remitter #710134 is]
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (July 1 [no year noted]) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Dave has been writing all of the boys all the time, but they don’t seem to receive the mail • Doesn’t think Connie will go home until the war is over • Is close to one of this brothers in location & will see him soon • Had two weeks added to their training
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (July 15, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • He finished his training & does not know what is going to happen next
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (August 1, 1945; Location—Camp Hood, Texas) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Received book and candies • Likes the fog weather • Isn’t sure where he will be stationed next
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (August 22, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Dave is worried about Peter because he hasn’t heard from him in about 3.5 months • Willie got malaria & they had to send him back to the States • Dave will take time & write to Willie so he can feel better • Doesn’t know when he will get a furlough
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (August 22, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Wants her to send him the Fresno Bee [newspaper] • Sent $3 home [money not in envelope]
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (August 22, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • He thanks her for sending him candy and cookies
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (August 27, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • He pays for all the mail • He tells her that he wonders where Peter is
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (September 4, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Sends $50 to save [money not in envelope] • Tells her to use any money if she needs it • Transferred to another place
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (September 13, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Willie will be in the occupational troops with the forty-first will be in Northern Japan • Knows that Connie is going home soon.
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (September 28, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • He complains about one of his brothers: Willie • He’s trying to get Willie some T-shirts • He questions what Willie does with all his money if he doesn’t send any home and makes about $100 • Scott finally went home • Dave was transferred to D CO. • Asked her to send him Pete’s address
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (October 16, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Moved to another division & is kept busy • Works on motor pool & trucks that come in for repair • Asked if Connie got a discharge or furlough? • Sent Willie 3 shirts • Asks about his brothers
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (November 3, 1945) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Asks where Scott is and if he is still a First Lieutenant. Asked if Scott wore his medals at his wedding [Dave had just found out that Scott got married] • Dave hopes they took pictures • Asks if Scott’s wife likes Fresno
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (November 16, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Hopes he gets with a good bunch of guys in his group • Addresses other siblings in letter
  - Letter to Everybody from Dave (January 30, 1946) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Has been training • Asked if they received the pictures he sent
  - Letter to Everybody from Dave (February 1946) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Called Scott the night before & met up • Scott’s wife name – Judy • Description of Judy: good-looking, same height as Scott • Dave's base [Fort Lawton] is only bout 4 miles away from where Scott now lives • Weather—rainy, cloudy, no sunlight
  - Letter to Everybody from Dave (March 21, 1946 (Location—Korea)) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • It took 23 days to get to Korea & traveled by boat • Traveling was rough—the water was real rough that two men were washed overboard and a few were hurt so they had to drop them off in Hawaii • Close to southern Japan they had the roughest water in the trip, there was a storm • Everyone was pretty scared & worried • The day they got there the 40th division was just going back to the US • Weather—so cold that even the water fountains have icicles & wears a lot of clothes to keep him warm • Living in a factory
  - "Semper Primus: The Story of the First Infantry". Headquarters First Infantry APO 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    [typed up history of the First Infantry sent from Dave to Anne May 15, 1946]
  - Letter to Everybody from Dave (June 12, 1946) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Weather—Rainy & gloomy • He’s been on guard so he doesn’t really have time • Is going to send two money orders that he wants them to deposit ($100 & $27) [money not in envelope] • Sent another home $100 about two weeks ago
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (June 27, 1946) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Asked if Willie is home yet or still in Japan • Sent a money order of $227 ($100 in first letter & $127 in second) [money is not in envelope] • Won a camera & a 6 tube radio • Is sending pictures he wants saved [pictures not in envelope] • Says if John & Mary ask why he hasn’t written to tell them there isn’t anything to write about
  - Letter to Everybody from Dave (July 3, 1946) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Sends a $53 money order home before it can get lost [money order is not in envelope] • There was a riot downtown but broke up once the US soliders got their rifles and arms on. "They were only trying to fight for rice." • Tells them that he wrote Willie but still hasn’t received any reply
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (July 12, 1946) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Asks for some films & variety of candy • Film—to take pictures of places he has went to • Ask what Emma was doing in town, he thought she was going to stay on the ranch with the boys
  - Letter to Everybody from Dave (August 12, 1946) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Asked about Pete & Connie on the ranch • Asked about the crops being ready to get picked • Asked if Hank [Henry] has got a car yet • Asked if they are going to move soon since winter is near • Will not be until next summer that he goes home • Hasn’t had a day off in 21 days • Asked if Willie is home yet • Sending $80 [money is not in envelope]
  - Letter to Everybody from Dave (August 22, 1946[?]) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Has been busy pulling guard • Had one day off in 30 days • Is sending all his money home because he has no use for it over there • Will send another $80 • He does not gamble • To Anne – he wants her to keep track of the money she is spending on him because he wants to pay her back • Asks that next time she sends a package, could she send some gum, hair oil, candy, radio tube
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (October 9, 1946) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Anne is saving his money • He has $65 he wants to save • Sent $25 home [money not in envelope]
  - Letter to Bill from Dave (November 18 [no year noted]) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • Tells him that he does remember where anything was back home • When he went to home in October, he couldn’t hardly find anything • It has been almost two years that he left home • Asks about the number of tins of raisins they had & some of the work they’ll do on ranch/farm • Talks about driving the tracker that summer • Asks if Peter has his own car yet or if he’s using Connie’s • Christmas & Happy New Year letter
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (December 4, 1946) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • He talks about weather – how it is extremely cold there • Told her not to expect him for Christmas • He will be home about February or March if nothing happens • Talks about how he sees big planes & names different types of planes • He’s far from the ocean & doesn’t know where they are going • Sent her a radio so she can get it fixed
  - "A Mother's Prayer for Her Solider Son". Sent from Dave to Anne, n.d. [envelope stamped December 4, 1946] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter to Anne Rube from Dave (December 6, 1946 (Location—Yokahoma, Japan)) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    • He’s in Japan & will be there for the next two months • He likes it better there: they are cleaner and dress better • He never wants to go to Korea again • Issue with writing letters – addresses change & sometimes it takes up to a week to get permanent address for that location
- Series 6: Letters from Henry Rube
  - Postcard/Letter to Parents (August 8, 1941) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Sent Scott’s new address
  - Postcard/Letter to Parents (August 27, 1941) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • The rain has stopped the action • Will see Scott again
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (December 15, 1941) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Left camp & went to Los Angeles • Connie is with him & gave him a Christmas card from Mary & Anne
  - Letter to Willie, Dave & Emma from Henry (March 11, 1942) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Letter lecturing his siblings • Says that they should listen to Dad, mom, & Kay instead of Mary, Anne, & Pete • He’s heard that they haven’t been treating their father well • Said that Dad is doing the best he can for them • Said that the lady that Dad wants to marry is a good woman & to not believe what Mary, Anne, & Pete are saying about the lady because they don’t know her • Says that Dad wants a lady that can take care of Willie, Dave, & Emma [the siblings left at home] & the house • Knows that Anne will soon be old enough to work & marry • Told them to not listen to what people are saying about Dad; that they are jealous because Dad is better off than them • Says that if they behave themselves they will give them something
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 4, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)
    • Sorry for the confusion regarding the recent postcard that he sent that made them think he had gone overseas. He just used the only paper he could find to give them his new address • He is actually located in Louisiana • Told them to get Willie away from Kellner [no first name] and if they can’t control him, send him to the army
  - Letter to Parents from Henry (July 16, 1943) (Box 1, Folder 6)